Finding Aid for Rice Aner Beal papers, 1843-1883
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Rice Aner Beal papers 1843-1883
Beal, Rice Aner, 1823-1883.
4 linear feet
85749 Aa 2
Businessman, of Washtenaw County, Michigan, publisher of Ann Arbor Courier, and chairman of Executive Committee, Michigan Republican Party. Correspondence, account books, business records, receipts, deeds, and other financial records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Albert Jacobs (donor no. 3046 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Rice Aner Beal was a Washtenaw County businessman and politician. He was publisher of the Ann Arbor Courier and active in the state Republican Party in the 1870s.
The Rice Aner Beal collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Political and Legal papers; and Financial records. Among Rice Beal's correspondents were such personages as James B. Angell, Henry P. Baldwin, Zachariah Chandler, Isaac P. Christiancy, Omar D. Conger, Thomas M. Cooley, Charles M. Croswell, Byron M. Cutcheon, Thomas W. Ferry, James F. Joy, James McMillan, Thomas W. Palmer, John T. Rich, Moses C. Tyler, Henry Waldron, Edwin Willits, and Alexander Winchell. Within the Political and Legal papers series there are materials relating to litigation with Alvin W. Chase and Silas Douglas. His political career is partially documented in ledger volumes that he maintained while attending the Republican State conventions in 1878 and 1880. In these volumes, Beal listed the names of delegates with comments on their candidate preferences and abilities.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Banks and banking--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Beal, Rice Aner, 1823-1883.; Business records.; Chase, A. W. (Alvin Wood), 1817-1885.; Dexter (Mich.); Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.; Elections--Michigan--1878.; Elections--Michigan--1880.; Elections--Michigan--1882.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Republican Party (Mich.); Rose, Preston Benjamin, 1834-1912.; Antislavery movements--United States.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 13th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.; Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.; Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.; Conger, Omar Dwight, 1818-1898.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Croswell, Charles Miller, 1825-1886.; Cutcheon, Byron M., 1836-1908.; Ferry, Thomas White, 1827-1896.; Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.; Rich, John Treadway, 1841-1926.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Waldron, Henry, 1819-1880.; Willits, Mr. (Edwin), 1830-1896.; Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
- Correspondence
  - 1848-1883 and undated, 41 folders (Box 1)
    (some gaps in dates)
- Political and Legal papers
  - Petition, ca. 1861 concerning Crittenden Amendment to the U.S. Constitution (Box 1)
    (signed by Dexter area residents)
  - Papers, 1874-1875 concerning Rice A. Beal vs. Alvan W. Chase, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1876 concerning Silas Douglas vs. Rice A. Beal, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Papers, 1877 concerning the Board of Regents of the University of Michigan vs. Rose, Douglas et al. (Box 2)
  - Ledger, 1878 concerning the Republican State Convention (Box 2)
  - Ledger, 1880 concerning the Republican State Convention (Box 2)
- Financial records
  - Account books, 1847-1848 (Box 2)
  - Account books, 1857-1869 (Box 2)
  - Account books, 1879-1885 (Box 2)
  - Account books, 1843-1881 (Box 3)
  - Bills, receipts, deeds, mortgages, and other financial records (Box 4)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
1878 undated
Baldwin, Henry P. (Henry Porter), 1814-1892.
July 21, 1864, May 25, 1880
Chandler, Zachariah, 1813-1879.
Feb. 12, 1873, June 19, 1878, June 25, 1878
Christiancy, Isaac Peckham, 1812-1890.
Jan. 3, 1876, Oct. 4, 1877, Dec. 1877, Jan. 4, 1878, Jan. 29, 1878
Conger, Omar Dwight, 1818-1898.
Feb. 11, 1873, Nov. 23, 1880, Dec. 29, 1880
Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.
Jan. 8, 1874
Croswell, Charles Miller, 1825-1886.
Oct. 9, 1877, May 9, 1879, Mar. 11, 1880, Sept. 7, 1880
Cutcheon, Byron M., 1836-1908.
July 22, 1876, 1877-1878
Ferry, Thomas White, 1827-1896.
Feb. 17, 1881
Joy, James F. (James Frederick), 1810-1896.
Oct. 26, 1864, June 23, 1882, Sept. 25, 1882
MeMillan, James, 1838-1902.
Feb. 25, 1882, Apr. 30, 1882
Palmer, Thomas Witherell, 1830-1913.
Feb. 15, 1882, Jan.22, 1883
Rich, John Treadway, 1841-1926.
June 7, 1877
Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.
May 8, 1880, May 18, 1880, May 20, 1880
Waldron, Henry, 1819-1880.
1872-1876
Willits, Mr. (Edwin), 1830-1896.
1878, Nov. 26, 1880
Winchell, Alexander, 1824-1891.
Nov. 27, 1880